Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): Thank you very much Congresswoman Jayapal and words simply cannot embrace and capture how grateful we are for all of you to be here to bear witness and to be present to what is happening in our beloved state of Minnesota right now. Your presence here is incredibly important and impactful, shining a light on what is the single most unjust thing I've ever seen happen
to
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): state of Minnesota. The Trump administration's decision to target Minnesota and the Twin Cities flooding our streets with thousands of federal immigration agents is not about public safety. It's not about fraud. It's not even about immigration enforcement.
It is
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): because in the words of Donald Trump he believes that he won our state three times but he did not win
it in
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): the election.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): I'm quoting him, he's the one who said these words, not me. In fact, when he said what he said, it was so incredible
that
Speaker 2: I
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): had to replay it a few times to make sure that I heard that this was about vindictiveness and an election loss, not anything to do with any legitimate public interest. And you've heard already from the very accurate descriptions from our congressional presenters
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): that we've
Speaker 2: seen attacks on high schools, over 3,000 agents surge, warrantless searches, killings, shootings, and none of this has done anything to help Minnesota. In fact, it has hurt Minnesota. In fact, it has diminished economic activity in our state, deprived school's children from education, created barriers for public life, and has expanded costs
Speaker 2: our state you'll hear from both of our mayors how both of them are dealing with increased cost for overtime I'll leave that to them to describe but that is why
the three of us
Speaker 2: joined together with the state of Minnesota, Minneapolis, and St. Paul to sue the Trump administration over Operation Metro Surge.
Let me
Speaker 2: be clear. We're not suing because ICE is in Minnesota. They were in Minnesota last year. They were in Minnesota 10 years ago. We didn't sue them then. We sued them over this activity, which is unjustified, unconstitutional, damages our state, interferes with our sovereignty as a member of these United States.
Speaker 2: violates the administrative procedures act is arbitrary capricious and damaging to all of us. That is what this lawsuit is all about and I just want to note that you've heard much about how the behavior of ISIS is taxing our local law enforcement. But I want to be clear, local law enforcement is doing a good job. They're maintaining order in our state.
Speaker 2: The order, if to the degree there is a lack of it or a challenge, is directly and exclusively because of the metro surge authorized by the president of the United States.
This is,
Speaker 2: and so as he contemplates the Insurrection Act, please know that this is, we do not need federal authorities to help us maintain order. We need them to stop doing things.
That
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): is what is needed in this situation and that is what we're demanding in our lawsuit. So let me just
say
Speaker 2: that the family of Renee Nicole
Good and
Speaker 2: the family of everyone who's been thrown to the ground, beaten, harassed, arrested in a warrantless search, anyone whose business has been destroyed, had to face closing their business because of this conduct, that we are standing with you.
And
Speaker 2: we will not
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): stand by idly as this injustice unfolds. We will stand up and assert all means legal to protect the people of our state. I will yield back.